{
  "lesson1": [
    { "back": "わたし", "front": "I" },
    { "back": "わたしたち", "front": "we" },
    { "back": "あなた", "front": "you" },
    { "back": "あのひと", "front": "that person, he, she" },
    { "back": "あのかた", "front": "polite equivalent of あのひと" },
    { "back": "みなさん", "front": "ladies and gentlemen, all of you" },
    {
      "back": "〜さん",
      "front": "Mr., Ms. (title of respect added to a name)"
    },
    {
      "back": "〜ちゃん",
      "front": "(suffix often added to a child's name instead of 〜さん)"
    },
    { "back": "〜くん", "front": "(suffix often added to a boy's name)" },
    {
      "back": "〜じん",
      "front": "(suffix meaning 'a national of'; e.g., アメリカじん, an American)"
    },
    {
      "back": "せんせい",
      "front": "teacher, instructor (not used when referring to one's own job)"
    },
    { "back": "きょうし", "front": "teacher, instructor" },
    { "back": "がくせい", "front": "student" },
    { "back": "かいしゃいん", "front": "company employee" },
    {
      "back": "しゃいん",
      "front": "employee of ~ Company (used with a company's name; e.g., IMC のしゃいん)"
    },
    { "back": "ぎんこういん", "front": "bank employee" },
    { "back": "いしゃ", "front": "medical doctor" },
    { "back": "けんきゅうしゃ", "front": "researcher, scholar" },
    { "back": "エンジニア", "front": "engineer" },
    { "back": "だいがく", "front": "university" },
    { "back": "びょういん", "front": "hospital" },
    { "back": "でんき", "front": "electricity, light" },
    { "back": "だれ", "front": "who" },
    { "back": "どなた", "front": "polite equivalent of だれ" },
    { "back": "〜さい", "front": "~ years old" },
    { "back": "なんさい", "front": "how old" },
    { "back": "おいくつ", "front": "polite equivalent of なんさい" },
    { "back": "はい", "front": "yes" },
    { "back": "いいえ", "front": "no" },
    { "back": "しつれいですが", "front": "Excuse me, but" },
    { "back": "おなまえは?", "front": "May I have your name?" },
    { "back": "はじめまして。", "front": "How do you do?" },
    {
      "back": "どうぞよろしく おねがいします",
      "front": "Pleased to meet you."
    },
    { "back": "こちらは〜さんです。", "front": "This is Mr./Ms. ~." },
    { "back": "〜からきました", "front": "I came (come) from ~." }
  ],
  "lesson2": [
    { "back": "これ", "front": "this (thing near the speaker)" },
    {
      "back": "それ",
      "front": "that (thing far from the speaker, near the listener)"
    },
    {
      "back": "あれ",
      "front": "that (thing far from both the speaker and listener)"
    },
    { "back": "この~", "front": "this ~, this ~ here" },
    { "back": "その~", "front": "that ~, that ~ near you" },
    { "back": "あの~", "front": "that ~, that ~ over there" },
    { "back": "ほん", "front": "book" },
    { "back": "じしょ", "front": "dictionary" },
    { "back": "ざっし", "front": "magazine" },
    { "back": "しんぶん", "front": "newspaper" },
    { "back": "ノート", "front": "notebook" },
    { "back": "てちょう", "front": "pocket notebook" },
    { "back": "めいし", "front": "business card" },
    { "back": "カード", "front": "card" },
    { "back": "テレホンカード", "front": "telephone card" },
    { "back": "えんぴつ", "front": "pencil" },
    { "back": "ボールペン", "front": "ballpoint pen" },
    {
      "back": "シャープペンシル",
      "front": "mechanical pencil, propelling pencil"
    },
    { "back": "かぎ", "front": "key" },
    { "back": "とけい", "front": "watch, clock" },
    { "back": "かさ", "front": "umbrella" },
    { "back": "かばん", "front": "bag, briefcase" },
    { "back": "カセットテープ", "front": "cassette tape" },
    { "back": "テープレコーダー", "front": "tape recorder" },
    { "back": "テレビ", "front": "television" },
    { "back": "ラジオ", "front": "radio" },
    { "back": "カメラ", "front": "camera" },
    { "back": "コンピューター", "front": "computer" },
    { "back": "じどうしゃ", "front": "automobile, car" },
    { "back": "つくえ", "front": "desk" },
    { "back": "いす", "front": "chair" },
    { "back": "チョコレート", "front": "chocolate" },
    { "back": "コーヒー", "front": "coffee" },
    { "back": "えいご", "front": "the English language" },
    { "back": "にほんご", "front": "the Japanese language" },
    { "back": "~ご", "front": "~ language" },
    { "back": "なん", "front": "what" },
    { "back": "そう", "front": "so" },
    { "back": "ちがいます", "front": "No, it isn't. You are wrong." },
    { "back": "そうですか", "front": "I see./Is that so?" },
    { "back": "あのう", "front": "well...(used to show hesitation)" },
    {
      "back": "ほんのきもちです",
      "front": "It's nothing./It's a token of my gratitude."
    },
    {
      "back": "どうぞ",
      "front": "Please./Here you are. (used when offering someone something)"
    },
    { "back": "どうも", "front": "Well, thanks." },
    { "back": "どうもありがとう", "front": "Thank you very much" },
    { "back": "ございます", "front": "very much" },
    {
      "back": "これからあせわになります",
      "front": "I hope for your kind assistance hereafter."
    },
    {
      "back": "こちらこそよろしく",
      "front": "I am pleased to meet you. (response to どうぞよろしく)"
    }
  ],
  "lesson3": [
    { "back": "ここ", "front": "here, this place" },
    { "back": "そこ", "front": "there, that place near you" },
    { "back": "あそこ", "front": "that place over there" },
    { "back": "どこ", "front": "where, what place?" },
    { "back": "こちら", "front": "this way, this place (polite ここ)" },
    {
      "back": "そちら",
      "front": "that way, that place near you (polite そこ)"
    },
    {
      "back": "あちら",
      "front": "that way, that place over there (polite あそこ)"
    },
    { "back": "どちら", "front": "which way, where (polite どこ)" },
    { "back": "きょうしつ 教室", "front": "classroom" },
    { "back": "しょくどう 食堂", "front": "dining hall, canteen" },
    { "back": "じむしょ 事務所", "front": "office" },
    { "back": "かいぎしつ 会議室", "front": "conference room, assembly room" },
    { "back": "うけつけ 受付", "front": "reception desk" },
    { "back": "ロビー", "front": "lobby" },
    { "back": "へや 部屋", "front": "room" },
    { "back": "トイレ(おてあらい) (お手洗い)", "front": "toilet" },
    { "back": "かいだん 階段", "front": "staircase" },
    { "back": "エレベーター", "front": "elevator, lift" },
    { "back": "エスカレーター", "front": "escalator" },
    { "back": "[お]くに [お]国", "front": "country" },
    { "back": "かいしゃ 会社", "front": "work, company" },
    { "back": "うち 家", "front": "house, home" },
    { "back": "でんわ 電話", "front": "telephone, telephone call" },
    { "back": "くつ 靴", "front": "shoes" },
    { "back": "ネクタイ", "front": "necktie" },
    { "back": "ワイン", "front": "wine" },
    { "back": "たばこ 煙草", "front": "tobacco, cigarette" },
    {
      "back": "うりば 売り場",
      "front": "department, counter (in a department store)"
    },
    { "back": "ちか 地下", "front": "basement" },
    { "back": "〜かい(〜がい) 〜階", "front": "~th floor" },
    { "back": "なんがい 何階", "front": "what floor" },
    { "back": "〜えん 〜円", "front": "~yen" },
    { "back": "いくら 幾ら", "front": "how much" },
    { "back": "ひゃく 百", "front": "hundred" },
    { "back": "せん 千", "front": "thousand" },
    { "back": "まん 万", "front": "ten thousand" },
    { "back": "すみません。", "front": "Excuse me." },
    { "back": "~でございます。", "front": "(polite equivalent of です)" },
    {
      "back": "[~を] みせてください。 [~を] 見せてください。",
      "front": "Please show me [~]."
    },
    { "back": "じゃ", "front": "well, then, in that case" },
    { "back": "[~を]くだざい。", "front": "Give me [~], please." }
  ],
  "lesson4": [
    { "back": "おきます", "front": "get up, wake up" },
    { "back": "ねます", "front": "sleep, go to bed" },
    { "back": "はたらきます", "front": "work" },
    { "back": "やすみます", "front": "take a rest, take a holiday" },
    { "back": "べんきょうします", "front": "study" },
    { "back": "おわります", "front": "finish" },
    { "back": "デパート", "front": "department store" },
    { "back": "ぎんこう", "front": "bank" },
    { "back": "ゆうびんきょく", "front": "post office" },
    { "back": "としょかん", "front": "library" },
    { "back": "びじゅつかん", "front": "art museum" },
    { "back": "いま", "front": "now" },
    { "back": "~じ", "front": "~o'clock" },
    { "back": "~ふん (〜ぷん)", "front": "~minute" },
    { "back": "はん", "front": "half" },
    { "back": "なんじ", "front": "what time" },
    { "back": "なんぷん", "front": "what minute" },
    { "back": "ごぜん", "front": "a.m., morning" },
    { "back": "ごご", "front": "p.m., afternoon" },
    { "back": "あさ", "front": "morning" },
    { "back": "ひる", "front": "daytime, noon" },
    { "back": "ばん(よる)", "front": "night, evening" },
    { "back": "おととい", "front": "the day before yesterday" },
    { "back": "きのう", "front": "yesterday" },
    { "back": "きょう", "front": "today" },
    { "back": "あした", "front": "tomorrow" },
    { "back": "あさって", "front": "the day after tomorrow" },
    { "back": "けさ", "front": "this morning" },
    { "back": "こんばん", "front": "this evening, tonight" },
    { "back": "やすみ", "front": "rest, a holiday, a day off" },
    { "back": "ひるやすみ", "front": "lunchtime" },
    { "back": "まいあさ", "front": "every morning" },
    { "back": "まいばん", "front": "every evening" },
    { "back": "まいにち", "front": "every day" },
    { "back": "げつようび", "front": "Monday" },
    { "back": "かようび", "front": "Tuesday" },
    { "back": "すいようび", "front": "Wednesday" },
    { "back": "もくようび", "front": "Thursday" },
    { "back": "きんようび", "front": "Friday" },
    { "back": "どようび", "front": "Saturday" },
    { "back": "にちようび", "front": "Sunday" },
    { "back": "なんようび", "front": "what day of the week" },
    { "back": "ばんごう", "front": "number" },
    { "back": "なんばん", "front": "what number" },
    { "back": "~から", "front": "from ~" },
    { "back": "~まで", "front": "up to ~, until ~" },
    { "back": "~と~", "front": "and (used to connect nouns)" },
    { "back": "そちら", "front": "your place" },
    {
      "back": "たいへんですね",
      "front": "That's tough, isn't it? (used when expressing sympathy)"
    },
    { "back": "えーと", "front": "well, let me see" },
    { "back": "104", "front": "information, directory assistance" },
    { "back": "おねがいします", "front": "Please. (lit. ask for a favor)" },
    { "back": "かしこまりました", "front": "Certainly (sir, madam)." },
    {
      "back": "おといあわせのばんごう",
      "front": "the number being inquired about"
    },
    {
      "back": "[どうも]ありがとうごさいました",
      "front": "Thank you very much."
    }
  ],
  "lesson5": [
    { "back": "いきます", "front": "go" },
    { "back": "きます", "front": "come" },
    { "back": "かえります", "front": "go home, return" },
    { "back": "がっこう", "front": "school" },
    { "back": "スーパー", "front": "supermarket" },
    { "back": "えき", "front": "station" },
    { "back": "ひこうき", "front": "airplane" },
    { "back": "ふね", "front": "ship" },
    { "back": "でんしゃ", "front": "electric train" },
    { "back": "ちかてつ", "front": "subway, underground" },
    { "back": "しんかんせん", "front": "the Shinkansen, the bullet train" },
    { "back": "バス", "front": "bus" },
    { "back": "タクシー", "front": "taxi" },
    { "back": "じてんしゃ", "front": "bicycle" },
    { "back": "あるいて", "front": "on foot" },
    { "back": "ひと", "front": "person, people" },
    { "back": "ともだち", "front": "friend" },
    { "back": "かれ", "front": "he, boyfriend, lover" },
    { "back": "かのじょ", "front": "she, girlfriend, lover" },
    { "back": "かぞく", "front": "family" },
    { "back": "ひとりで", "front": "alone, by oneself" },
    { "back": "せんしゅう", "front": "last week" },
    { "back": "こんしゅう", "front": "this week" },
    { "back": "らいしゅう", "front": "next week" },
    { "back": "せんげつ", "front": "last month" },
    { "back": "こんげつ", "front": "this month" },
    { "back": "らいげつ", "front": "next month" },
    { "back": "きょねん", "front": "last year" },
    { "back": "ことし", "front": "this year" },
    { "back": "らいねん", "front": "next year" },
    { "back": "~がつ", "front": "~th month of the year" },
    { "back": "なんがつ", "front": "what month" },
    { "back": "ついたち", "front": "first day of the month" },
    { "back": "ふつか", "front": "second, two days" },
    { "back": "みっか", "front": "third, three days" },
    { "back": "よっか", "front": "fourth, four days" },
    { "back": "いつか", "front": "fifth, five days" },
    { "back": "むいか", "front": "sixth, six days" },
    { "back": "なのか", "front": "seventh, seven days" },
    { "back": "ようか", "front": "eighth, eight days" },
    { "back": "ここのか", "front": "ninth, nine days" },
    { "back": "とおか", "front": "tenth, ten days" },
    { "back": "じゅうよっか", "front": "fourteenth, fourteen days" },
    { "back": "はつか", "front": "twentieth, twenty days" },
    { "back": "にじゅうよっか", "front": "twenty fourth, twenty four days" },
    { "back": "~にち", "front": "~th day of the month, ~days" },
    { "back": "なんにち", "front": "which day of the month, how many days" },
    { "back": "いつ", "front": "when" },
    { "back": "たんじょうび", "front": "birthday" },
    { "back": "ふつう", "front": "local (train)" },
    { "back": "きゅうこう", "front": "rapid" },
    { "back": "とっきゅう", "front": "express" },
    { "back": "つぎの", "front": "next" },
    {
      "back": "どういたしまして",
      "front": "You're welcome./Don't mention it."
    },
    { "back": "~ばんせん", "front": "platform ~, ~th platform" }
  ],
  "lesson6": [
    { "back": "たべます", "front": "eat" },
    { "back": "のみます", "front": "drink" },
    { "back": "すいます[たばこを~]", "front": "smoke [a cigarette]" },
    { "back": "みます", "front": "see, look at, watch" },
    { "back": "ききます", "front": "hear, listen" },
    { "back": "よみます", "front": "read" },
    { "back": "かきます", "front": "write, draw, paint" },
    { "back": "かいます", "front": "buy" },
    { "back": "とります[しゃしんを~]", "front": "take [a photograph]" },
    { "back": "します", "front": "do" },
    { "back": "あいます[ともだちに~]", "front": "meet [a friend]" },
    { "back": "ごはん", "front": "a meal, cooked rice" },
    { "back": "あさごはん", "front": "breakfast" },
    { "back": "ひるごはん", "front": "lunch" },
    { "back": "ばんごはん", "front": "supper" },
    { "back": "パン", "front": "bread" },
    { "back": "たまご", "front": "egg" },
    { "back": "にく", "front": "meat" },
    { "back": "さかな", "front": "fish" },
    { "back": "やさい", "front": "vegetable" },
    { "back": "くだもの", "front": "fruit" },
    { "back": "みず", "front": "water" },
    { "back": "おちゃ", "front": "tea, green tea" },
    { "back": "こうちゃ", "front": "black tea" },
    { "back": "ぎゅうにゅう(ミリク)", "front": "milk" },
    { "back": "ジュース", "front": "juice" },
    { "back": "ビール", "front": "beer" },
    { "back": "[お]さけ", "front": "alcohol, Japanese rice wine" },
    { "back": "ビデオ", "front": "video" },
    { "back": "えいが", "front": "movie" },
    { "back": "CD", "front": "CD, compact disk" },
    { "back": "てがみ", "front": "letter" },
    { "back": "レポート", "front": "report" },
    { "back": "しゃしん", "front": "photograph" },
    { "back": "みせ", "front": "store, shop" },
    { "back": "レストラン", "front": "restaurant" },
    { "back": "にわ", "front": "garden" },
    { "back": "しゅくだい", "front": "homework (~をします: do homework)" },
    { "back": "テニス", "front": "tennis" },
    {
      "back": "サッカー",
      "front": "soccer, football (~をします: play soccer)"
    },
    {
      "back": "[お]はなみ",
      "front": "cherry-blossom viewing (~をします: go cherry-blossom viewing)"
    },
    { "back": "なに", "front": "what" },
    { "back": "いっしょに", "front": "together" },
    { "back": "ちょっと", "front": "a little while, a little bit" },
    { "back": "いつも", "front": "always, usually" },
    { "back": "ときどき", "front": "sometimes" },
    { "back": "それから", "front": "after that, and then" },
    { "back": "ええ", "front": "yes" },
    { "back": "いいですね", "front": "That's good" },
    { "back": "わかりました", "front": "I see" },
    { "back": "なんですか", "front": "Yes?" },
    { "back": "じゃ、また[あした]", "front": "See you [tomorrow]" }
  ],
  "lesson7": [
    { "back": "きります", "front": "cut, slice" },
    { "back": "おくります", "front": "send" },
    { "back": "あげます", "front": "give" },
    { "back": "もらいます", "front": "receive" },
    { "back": "かします", "front": "lend" },
    { "back": "かります", "front": "borrow" },
    { "back": "おしえます", "front": "teach" },
    { "back": "ならいます", "front": "learn" },
    { "back": "かけます[でんわを~]", "front": "make [a telephone call]" },
    { "back": "て", "front": "hand, arm" },
    { "back": "はし", "front": "chopsticks" },
    { "back": "スプーン", "front": "spoon" },
    { "back": "ナイフ", "front": "knife" },
    { "back": "フォーク", "front": "fork" },
    { "back": "はさみ", "front": "scissors" },
    { "back": "ファクス", "front": "fax" },
    { "back": "ワープロ", "front": "word processor" },
    { "back": "パソコン", "front": "personal computer" },
    { "back": "パンチ", "front": "punch" },
    { "back": "ホッチキス", "front": "stapler" },
    { "back": "セロテープ", "front": "Scotch tape, clear adhesive tape" },
    { "back": "けしゴマ", "front": "eraser" },
    { "back": "かみ", "front": "paper" },
    { "back": "はな", "front": "flower, blossom" },
    { "back": "シャツ", "front": "shirt" },
    { "back": "プレゼント", "front": "present, gift" },
    { "back": "にもつ", "front": "baggage, parcel" },
    { "back": "おかね", "front": "money" },
    { "back": "きっぷ", "front": "ticket" },
    { "back": "クリスマス", "front": "Christmas" },
    { "back": "ちち", "front": "(my) father" },
    { "back": "はは", "front": "(my) mother" },
    { "back": "おとうさん", "front": "(someone else's) father" },
    { "back": "おかあさん", "front": "(someone else's) mother" },
    { "back": "もう", "front": "already" },
    { "back": "まだ", "front": "not yet" },
    { "back": "これから", "front": "from now on, soon" },
    { "back": "[~、]すてきです ね", "front": "What a nice [~]!" },
    {
      "back": "ごめんください",
      "front": "Excuse me./Anybody home?/May I come in?"
    },
    {
      "back": "いらっしゃい",
      "front": "How nice of you to come. (lit. Welcome.)"
    },
    { "back": "どうぞおあがりください", "front": "Do come in." },
    {
      "back": "しつれいします",
      "front": "Thank you./May I? (lit. I'm afraid I will be disturbing you.)"
    },
    {
      "back": "[~は]いかがですか",
      "front": "Won't you have [~]?/Would you like to have [~]?"
    },
    {
      "back": "いただきます",
      "front": "Thank you./I accept. (said before starting to eat or drink.)"
    },
    { "back": "りょこう", "front": "trip, tour" },
    { "back": "おみやげ", "front": "souvenir, present" }
  ],
  "lesson8": [
    
      { "back": "ハンサム[な]", "front": "handsome" },
      { "back": "きれい[な]", "front": "beautiful, clean" },
      { "back": "しずか[な]", "front": "quiet" },
      { "back": "にぎやか[な]", "front": "lively" },
      { "back": "ゆうめい[な]", "front": "famous" },
      { "back": "しんせつ[な]", "front": "kind" },
      { "back": "げんき[な]", "front": "healthy, sound, cheerful" },
      { "back": "ひま[な]", "front": "free (time)" },
      { "back": "べんり[な]", "front": "convenient" },
      { "back": "すてき[な]", "front": "fine, nice, wonderful" },
      { "back": "おおきい", "front": "big, large" },
      { "back": "ちいさい", "front": "small, little" },
      { "back": "あたらしい", "front": "new" },
      { "back": "ふるい", "front": "old (not of age)" },
      { "back": "いい(よい)", "front": "good" },
      { "back": "わるい", "front": "bad" },
      { "back": "あつい", "front": "hot" },
      { "back": "さむい", "front": "cold (referring to temperature)" },
      { "back": "つめたい", "front": "cold (referring to touch, as a drink)" },
      { "back": "むずかしい", "front": "difficult" },
      { "back": "やさしい", "front": "easy" },
      { "back": "たかい", "front": "expensive, tall, high" },
      { "back": "やすい", "front": "inexpensive" },
      { "back": "ひくい", "front": "low" },
      { "back": "おもしろい", "front": "interesting" },
      { "back": "おいしい", "front": "delicious, tasty" },
      { "back": "いそがしい", "front": "busy" },
      { "back": "たのしい", "front": "enjoyable" },
      { "back": "しろい", "front": "white" },
      { "back": "くろい", "front": "black" },
      { "back": "あかい", "front": "red" },
      { "back": "あおい", "front": "blue" },
      { "back": "さくら", "front": "cherry (blossom)" },
      { "back": "やま", "front": "mountain" },
      { "back": "まち", "front": "town, city" },
      { "back": "たべもの", "front": "food" },
      { "back": "くるま", "front": "car, vehicle" },
      { "back": "ところ", "front": "place" },
      { "back": "りょう", "front": "dormitory" },
      { "back": "べんきょう", "front": "study" },
      { "back": "せいかつ", "front": "life" },
      {
        "back": "[お]しごと",
        "front": "work, business (~おしごとをします: do one's job, work)"
      },
      { "back": "どう", "front": "how" },
      { "back": "どんな~", "front": "what kind of ~" },
      { "back": "どれ", "front": "which one (of three or more)" },
      { "back": "とても", "front": "very" },
      { "back": "あまり", "front": "not so (used with negatives)" },
      { "back": "そして", "front": "and (used to connect sentences)" },
      { "back": "~が、~", "front": "~, but ~" },
      { "back": "おげんきですか", "front": "How are you?" },
      { "back": "そうですね", "front": "Well let me see. (pausing)" },
      {
        "back": "にほんのせいかつになれましたか",
        "front": "Have you got used to the life in Japan?"
      },
      {
        "back": "[~、]もういっぱいいかがですか",
        "front": "Won't you have another cup of [~]?"
      },
      { "back": "いいえ、けっこうです", "front": "No, thank you." },
      { "back": "もう~です[ね]", "front": "It's already ~ [, isn't it?]" },
      {
        "back": "そろそろしつれいします",
        "front": "It's almost time to leave now."
      },
      { "back": "またいらっしゃってください", "front": "Please come again." }
    
  ],
  "lesson9": [
    
      { "back": "わかります[が]", "front": "understand" },
      { "back": "あります[が]", "front": "have" },
      { "back": "すき[な]", "front": "like" },
      { "back": "きらい[な]", "front": "dislike" },
      { "back": "じょうず[な]", "front": "good at" },
      { "back": "へた[な]", "front": "poor at" },
      { "back": "りょうり", "front": "dish (cooked food), cooking" },
      { "back": "のみもの", "front": "drinks" },
      { "back": "スポーツ", "front": "sport (~をします: play sports)" },
      { "back": "やきゅう", "front": "baseball (~をします: play baseball)" },
      { "back": "ダンス", "front": "dance (~をします: dance)" },
      { "back": "おんがく", "front": "music" },
      { "back": "うた", "front": "song" },
      { "back": "クラシック", "front": "classical music" },
      { "back": "ジャズ", "front": "jazz" },
      { "back": "コンサート", "front": "concert" },
      { "back": "カラオケ", "front": "karaoke" },
      {
        "back": "かぶき",
        "front": "Kabuki (traditional Japanese musical drama)"
      },
      { "back": "え", "front": "picture, drawing" },
      { "back": "じ", "front": "letter, character" },
      { "back": "かんじ", "front": "Chinese characters" },
      { "back": "ひらがな", "front": "Hiragana script" },
      { "back": "かたかな", "front": "Katakana script" },
      { "back": "ローマじ", "front": "the Roman alphabet" },
      { "back": "こまかいおかね", "front": "small change" },
      { "back": "チケット", "front": "ticket" },
      { "back": "じかん", "front": "time" },
      { "back": "ようじ", "front": "something to do, errand" },
      { "back": "やくそく", "front": "appointment, promise" },
      { "back": "ごしゅじん", "front": "(someone else's) husband" },
      { "back": "おっと/しゅじん", "front": "(my) husband" },
      { "back": "おくさん", "front": "(someone else's) wife" },
      { "back": "つま/かない", "front": "(my) wife" },
      { "back": "こども", "front": "child" },
      { "back": "よく", "front": "well, much" },
      { "back": "だいたい", "front": "mostly, roughly" },
      { "back": "たくさん", "front": "many, much" },
      { "back": "すこし", "front": "a little, a few" },
      { "back": "ぜんぜん", "front": "not at all (used with negatives)" },
      { "back": "はやく", "front": "early, quickly, fast" },
      { "back": "~から", "front": "because ~" },
      { "back": "どうして", "front": "why" },
      {
        "back": "ぎんねんです[ね]",
        "front": "I'm sorry (to hear that)./That's a pity."
      },
      { "back": "すみません", "front": "I am sorry." },
      { "back": "もしもし", "front": "hello (used on phone)" },
      { "back": "ああ", "front": "oh" },
      { "back": "いっしょにいかがですか", "front": "Won't you join me (us)?" },
      {
        "back": "[~は]ちょっと...",
        "front": "[~] is a bit difficult. (an euphemism used when declining an invitation)"
      },
      { "back": "だめですか", "front": "So you cannot (come)?" },
      {
        "back": "またこんどおねがいします",
        "front": "Please ask me again some other time. (when refusing an invitation indirectly, considering someone's feelings)"
      }
    
  ],
  "lesson10": [
    
      {
        "back": "います[が]",
        "front": "exist, be (referring to animate things)"
      },
      {
        "back": "あります[が]",
        "front": "exist, be (referring to inanimate things)"
      },
      { "back": "いろいろ[な]", "front": "various" },
      { "back": "おとこのひと", "front": "man" },
      { "back": "おんなのひと", "front": "woman" },
      { "back": "おとこのこ", "front": "boy" },
      { "back": "おんなのこ", "front": "girl" },
      { "back": "いぬ", "front": "dog" },
      { "back": "ねこ", "front": "cat" },
      { "back": "き", "front": "tree" },
      { "back": "もの", "front": "thing" },
      { "back": "フィルム", "front": "film" },
      { "back": "でんち", "front": "battery" },
      { "back": "はこ", "front": "box" },
      { "back": "スイッチ", "front": "switch" },
      { "back": "れいぞうこ", "front": "refrigerator" },
      { "back": "テーブル", "front": "table" },
      { "back": "ベッド", "front": "bed" },
      { "back": "たな", "front": "shelf" },
      { "back": "ドア", "front": "door" },
      { "back": "まど", "front": "window" },
      { "back": "ポスト", "front": "mailbox, postbox" },
      { "back": "ビル", "front": "building" },
      { "back": "こうえん", "front": "park" },
      { "back": "きっさてん", "front": "coffee shop" },
      { "back": "ほんや", "front": "bookstore" },
      { "back": "~や", "front": "~ store" },
      {
        "back": "のりば",
        "front": "a fixed place to catch taxis, trains, etc."
      },
      { "back": "けん", "front": "prefecture" },
      { "back": "うえ", "front": "on, above, over" },
      { "back": "した", "front": "under, below, beneath" },
      { "back": "まえ", "front": "front, before" },
      { "back": "うしろ", "front": "back, behind" },
      { "back": "みぎ", "front": "right [side]" },
      { "back": "ひだり", "front": "left [side]" },
      { "back": "なか", "front": "in, inside" },
      { "back": "そと", "front": "outside" },
      { "back": "となり", "front": "next, next door" },
      { "back": "ちかく", "front": "near, vicinity" },
      { "back": "あいだ", "front": "between, among" },
      { "back": "~や~[など]", "front": "~, ~, and so on" },
      { "back": "いちばん~", "front": "the most ~ (いちばん うえ: the top)" },
      {
        "back": "~だんめ",
        "front": "the ~th shelf (だん is the counter for shelves)"
      },
      { "back": "[どうも]すみません。", "front": "Thank you." },
      { "back": "チリソース", "front": "chilli sauce" },
      { "back": "おく", "front": "the back" },
      { "back": "スパイスコーナー", "front": "spice corner" }
    
  ],
  "lesson11": [
    { "back": "います[こどもが~]", "front": "have [a child]" },
    { "back": "います[にほんに~]", "front": "stay, be [in Japan]" },
    { "back": "かかります", "front": "take (referring to time or money)" },
    { "back": "やすみます[かいしゃを~]", "front": "take a day off [work]" },
    { "back": "ひとつ", "front": "one (used when counting things)" },
    { "back": "ふたつ", "front": "two (used when counting things)" },
    { "back": "みっつ", "front": "three (used when counting things)" },
    { "back": "よっつ", "front": "four (used when counting things)" },
    { "back": "いつつ", "front": "five (used when counting things)" },
    { "back": "むっつ", "front": "six (used when counting things)" },
    { "back": "ななつ", "front": "seven (used when counting things)" },
    { "back": "やっつ", "front": "eight (used when counting things)" },
    { "back": "ここのつ", "front": "nine (used when counting things)" },
    { "back": "とお", "front": "ten (used when counting things)" },
    { "back": "いくつ", "front": "how many" },
    { "back": "ひとり", "front": "one person" },
    { "back": "ふたり", "front": "two people" },
    { "back": "~にん", "front": "~ people" },
    { "back": "~だい", "front": "counter for machines, cars, etc." },
    { "back": "~まい", "front": "counter for paper, stamps, etc." },
    { "back": "~かい", "front": "~ times" },
    { "back": "りんご", "front": "apple" },
    { "back": "みかん", "front": "mandarin orange" },
    { "back": "サンドイッチ", "front": "sandwich" },
    { "back": "カレー[ライス]", "front": "curry [and rice]" },
    { "back": "アイスクリーム", "front": "ice cream" },
    { "back": "きって", "front": "postage stamp" },
    { "back": "はがき", "front": "post card" },
    { "back": "ふうとう", "front": "envelope" },
    { "back": "そくたつ", "front": "special delivery" },
    { "back": "かきとめ", "front": "registered mail" },
    { "back": "エヤメール(こうくうびん)", "front": "airmail" },
    { "back": "ふなびん", "front": "sea mail" },
    { "back": "りょうしん", "front": "parents" },
    { "back": "きょうだい", "front": "brothers and sisters" },
    { "back": "あに", "front": "(my) elder brother" },
    { "back": "おにいさん", "front": "(someone else's) elder brother" },
    { "back": "あね", "front": "(my) elder sister" },
    { "back": "おねえさん", "front": "(someone else's) elder sister" },
    { "back": "おとうと", "front": "(my) younger brother" },
    { "back": "おとうとさん", "front": "(someone else's) younger brother" },
    { "back": "いもうと", "front": "(my) younger sister" },
    { "back": "いもうとさん", "front": "(someone else's) younger sister" },
    { "back": "がいこく", "front": "foreign country" },
    { "back": "~じかん", "front": "~ hours" },
    { "back": "~しゅうかん", "front": "~ weeks" },
    { "back": "~かげつ", "front": "~ months" },
    { "back": "~ねん", "front": "~ years" },
    { "back": "~ぐらい", "front": "about ~" },
    { "back": "~どのくらい", "front": "how long" },
    { "back": "ぜんぶで", "front": "in total" },
    { "back": "みんな", "front": "all, everything" },
    { "back": "~だけ", "front": "only ~" },
    {
      "back": "いらっしゃいませ。",
      "front": "Welcome./May I help you? (a greeting to a customer or a guest entering a shop, etc.)"
    },
    { "back": "いい[お]てんきですね。", "front": "Nice weather, isn't it?" },
    { "back": "おでかけですか。", "front": "Are you going out?" },
    { "back": "ちょっと~まで。", "front": "I'm just going to ~." },
    {
      "back": "いっていらっしゃい",
      "front": "So long. (lit. Go and come back.)"
    },
    {
      "back": "いってまいります",
      "front": "So long. (lit. I'm going and coming back.)"
    },
    { "back": "それから", "front": "and, furthermore" }
  ],
  "lesson12": [
    { "back": "かんたん[な]", "front": "easy, simple" },
    { "back": "ちかい", "front": "near" },
    { "back": "とおい", "front": "far" },
    { "back": "はやい", "front": "fast, early" },
    { "back": "おそい", "front": "slow, late" },
    { "back": "おおい[ひとが~]", "front": "many [people], much" },
    { "back": "すくない[ひとが~]", "front": "few [people], a little" },
    { "back": "あたたかい", "front": "warm" },
    { "back": "すずしい", "front": "cool" },
    { "back": "あまい", "front": "sweet" },
    { "back": "からい", "front": "hot (taste), spicy" },
    { "back": "おもい", "front": "heavy" },
    { "back": "かるい", "front": "light" },
    { "back": "いい[コーヒーが~]", "front": "prefer[coffee]" },
    { "back": "きせつ", "front": "season" },
    { "back": "はる", "front": "spring" },
    { "back": "なつ", "front": "summer" },
    { "back": "あき", "front": "autumn, fall" },
    { "back": "ふゆ", "front": "winter" },
    { "back": "てんき", "front": "weather" },
    { "back": "あめ", "front": "rain, rainy" },
    { "back": "ゆき", "front": "snow, snowy" },
    { "back": "くもり", "front": "cloudy" },
    { "back": "ホテル", "front": "hotel" },
    { "back": "くうこう", "front": "airport" },
    { "back": "うみ", "front": "sea, ocean" },
    { "back": "せかい", "front": "world" },
    { "back": "パーティー", "front": "party" },
    { "back": "[お]まつり", "front": "festival" },
    { "back": "しけん", "front": "examination" },
    { "back": "すきやき", "front": "sukiyaki (beef and vegetables hot pot)" },
    { "back": "さしみ", "front": "sashimi (sliced raw fish)" },
    {
      "back": "[お]すし",
      "front": "sushi (vinegar rice topped with raw fish)"
    },
    {
      "back": "てんぷら",
      "front": "tempura (seafood and vegetables deep fried in batter)"
    },
    {
      "back": "いけばな",
      "front": "flower arrangement (~をします: practice flower arrangement)"
    },
    { "back": "もみじ", "front": "maple, red leaves of autumn" },
    { "back": "どちら", "front": "which one (between two things)" },
    { "back": "どちらも", "front": "both" },
    { "back": "ずっと", "front": "by far" },
    { "back": "はじめて", "front": "for the first time" },
    { "back": "ただいま。", "front": "I'm home." },
    { "back": "おかえりなさい。", "front": "Welcome home." },
    { "back": "すごいですね。", "front": "That's amazing." },
    { "back": "でも", "front": "but" },
    { "back": "つかれました", "front": "(I'm) tired." }
  ],
  "lesson13": [
    { "back": "あそびます", "front": "enjoy oneself, play" },
    { "back": "およぎます", "front": "swim" },
    { "back": "むかえます", "front": "go to meet, welcome" },
    { "back": "つかれます", "front": "get tired" },
    { "back": "だします[てがみを~]", "front": "send [a letter]" },
    { "back": "はいります[きっさてんに~]", "front": "enter [a coffee shop]" },
    { "back": "でます[きっさてんを~]", "front": "go out [of a coffee shop]" },
    { "back": "けっこんします", "front": "marry, get married" },
    { "back": "かいものします", "front": "do shopping" },
    { "back": "しょくじします", "front": "have a meal, dine" },
    { "back": "さんぽします[こうえんを~]", "front": "take a walk [in a park]" },
    { "back": "たいへん[な]", "front": "hard, tough, severe, awful" },
    { "back": "ほしい", "front": "want (something)" },
    { "back": "さびしい", "front": "lonely" },
    { "back": "ひろい", "front": "wide, spacious" },
    { "back": "せまい", "front": "narrow, small (room, etc.)" },
    { "back": "しやくしょ", "front": "municipal office, city hall" },
    { "back": "プール", "front": "swimming pool" },
    { "back": "かわ", "front": "river" },
    { "back": "けいざい", "front": "economy" },
    { "back": "びじゅつ", "front": "fine arts" },
    { "back": "つり", "front": "fishing (~をします: fish, angle)" },
    { "back": "スキー", "front": "skiing (~をします: ski)" },
    {
      "back": "かいぎ",
      "front": "meeting, conference (~をします: hold a conference)"
    },
    { "back": "とうろく", "front": "registration (~をします: register)" },
    { "back": "しゅうまつ", "front": "weekend" },
    { "back": "~ごろ", "front": "about (time)" },
    { "back": "なにか", "front": "something" },
    { "back": "どこか", "front": "somewhere, some place" },
    { "back": "おなかがすきました。", "front": "(I'm) hungry." },
    { "back": "おなかがいっぱいです。", "front": "(I'm) full." },
    { "back": "のどがかわきました。", "front": "(I'm) thirsty." },
    { "back": "そうですね。", "front": "I agree with you." },
    {
      "back": "そうましょう。",
      "front": "Let's do that. (used when agreeing to someone's suggestion)"
    },
    { "back": "ごちゅうもんは?", "front": "May I take your order?" },
    { "back": "ていしょく", "front": "set meal" },
    { "back": "ぎゅうどん", "front": "bowl of rice topped with beef" },
    {
      "back": "[しょうしょう]おまちください。",
      "front": "Please wait [a moment.]"
    },
    { "back": "べつべつに", "front": "separately" }
  ],
  "lesson14": [
    { "back": "つけます", "front": "turn on" },
    { "back": "けします", "front": "turn off" },
    { "back": "あけます", "front": "open" },
    { "back": "しめます", "front": "close, shut" },
    { "back": "いそぎます", "front": "hurry" },
    { "back": "まちます", "front": "wait" },
    { "back": "とめます", "front": "stop, park" },
    { "back": "まがります[みぎへ~]", "front": "turn [to the right]" },
    { "back": "もちます", "front": "hold" },
    { "back": "とります", "front": "take, pass" },
    { "back": "てつだいます", "front": "help (with a task)" },
    { "back": "よびます", "front": "call" },
    { "back": "はなします", "front": "speak, talk" },
    { "back": "みせます", "front": "show" },
    { "back": "おしえます[じゅうしょを~]", "front": "tell [an address]" },
    { "back": "はじめます", "front": "start, begin" },
    { "back": "ふります[あめが~]", "front": "rain" },
    { "back": "コピーします", "front": "copy" },
    { "back": "エアコン", "front": "air conditioner" },
    { "back": "パスポート", "front": "passport" },
    { "back": "なまえ", "front": "name" },
    { "back": "じゅうしょ", "front": "address" },
    { "back": "ちず", "front": "map" },
    { "back": "しお", "front": "salt" },
    { "back": "さとう", "front": "sugar" },
    { "back": "よみかた", "front": "how to read, way of reading" },
    { "back": "~かた", "front": "how to ~, way of ~ing" },
    { "back": "ゆっくり", "front": "slowly, leisurely" },
    { "back": "すぐ", "front": "immediately" },
    { "back": "また", "front": "again" },
    { "back": "あとで", "front": "later" },
    { "back": "もうすこし", "front": "a little more" },
    { "back": "もう~", "front": "~ more, another ~" },
    { "back": "いいですよ。", "front": "Sure. / Certainly" },
    {
      "back": "さあ",
      "front": "right (used when encouraging some course of action)"
    },
    { "back": "あれ?", "front": "Oh!(in surprise or in wonder)" },
    {
      "back": "しんごうをみぎへまがってください。",
      "front": "Turn right at the signal."
    },
    { "back": "まっすぐ", "front": "straight" },
    { "back": "これでおねがいします。", "front": "I'd like to pay with this." },
    { "back": "おつり", "front": "change" }
  ],
  "lesson15": [
    { "back": "たちます", "front": "stand up" },
    { "back": "すわります", "front": "sit down" },
    { "back": "つかいます", "front": "use" },
    { "back": "おきます", "front": "put" },
    { "back": "つくります", "front": "make, produce" },
    { "back": "うります", "front": "sell" },
    { "back": "しります", "front": "get to know" },
    { "back": "すみます", "front": "be going to live" },
    { "back": "けんきゅうします", "front": "do research" },
    { "back": "しっています", "front": "know" },
    { "back": "すんでいます[おおさかに~]", "front": "live [in Osaka]" },
    { "back": "しりょう", "front": "materials, data" },
    { "back": "カタログ", "front": "catalog" },
    { "back": "じこくひょう", "front": "timetable" },
    { "back": "ふく", "front": "clothes" },
    { "back": "せいひん", "front": "products" },
    { "back": "ソフト", "front": "software" },
    { "back": "せんもん", "front": "speciality, field of study" },
    { "back": "はいしゃ", "front": "dentist, dentist's" },
    { "back": "とこや", "front": "barber, barber's" },
    { "back": "プレイガイド", "front": "(theatre) ticket agency" },
    { "back": "どくしん", "front": "single, unmarried" },
    { "back": "とくに", "front": "especially" },
    { "back": "おもいだします", "front": "remember, recollect" },
    { "back": "ごかぞく", "front": "your family" },
    {
      "back": "いらっしゃいます",
      "front": "be (honorific equivalent of います)"
    },
    { "back": "こうこう", "front": "senior high school" }
  ],
  "lesson16": [
    { "back": "のります[でんしゃに~]", "front": "ride, get on [a train]" },
    { "back": "おります[でんしゃを~]", "front": "get off [a train]" },
    { "back": "のりかえます", "front": "change (trains, etc.)" },
    { "back": "あびます[シャワーを~]", "front": "take [a shower]" },
    { "back": "いれます", "front": "put in, insert" },
    { "back": "だします", "front": "take out, withdraw" },
    { "back": "はいります[だいがくに~]", "front": "enter [university]" },
    { "back": "でます[だいがくを~]", "front": "graduate from [university]" },
    {
      "back": "やめます[かいしゃを~]",
      "front": "quit or retire from [a company], stop, give up"
    },
    { "back": "おします", "front": "press, push" },
    { "back": "わかい", "front": "young" },
    { "back": "ながい", "front": "long" },
    { "back": "みじかい", "front": "short" },
    { "back": "あかるい", "front": "bright, light" },
    { "back": "くらい", "front": "dark (depressed)" },
    { "back": "せがたかい", "front": "tall (referring to person)" },
    { "back": "あたまがいい", "front": "clever, smart" },
    { "back": "からだ", "front": "body" },
    { "back": "あたま", "front": "head" },
    { "back": "かみ", "front": "hair" },
    { "back": "かお", "front": "face" },
    { "back": "め", "front": "eye" },
    { "back": "みみ", "front": "ear" },
    { "back": "くち", "front": "mouth" },
    { "back": "は", "front": "tooth" },
    { "back": "おなか", "front": "stomach" },
    { "back": "あし", "front": "leg, foot" },
    { "back": "サービス", "front": "service" },
    { "back": "ジョギング", "front": "jogging (~をします :jog)" },
    { "back": "シャワー", "front": "shower" },
    { "back": "みどり", "front": "green, greenery" },
    { "back": "[お]てら", "front": "Buddhist temple" },
    { "back": "[お]じんじゃ", "front": "Shinto shrine" },
    { "back": "りゅうがくせい", "front": "foreign student" },
    { "back": "~ばん", "front": "number ~" },
    { "back": "どうやって", "front": "in what way, how" },
    { "back": "どの~", "front": "which ~ (used for three or more)" },
    {
      "back": "[いいえ、]まだまだです。",
      "front": "[No,] I still have a long way to go."
    },
    { "back": "おひきだしですか。", "front": "Are you making a withdrawal?" },
    { "back": "まず", "front": "first of all" },
    { "back": "キャッシュカード", "front": "cash dispensing card" },
    {
      "back": "あんしょうばんごう",
      "front": "personal identification number, PIN"
    },
    { "back": "つぎに", "front": "next, as a next step" },
    { "back": "きんがく", "front": "amount of money" },
    { "back": "かくにん", "front": "confirmation (~します: confirm)" },
    { "back": "ボタン", "front": "button" }
  ],
  "lesson17": [
    { "back": "おぼえます", "front": "memorise" },
    { "back": "わすれます", "front": "forget" },
    { "back": "なくします", "front": "lose" },
    { "back": "だします[レポートを~]", "front": "hand in [a report]" },
    { "back": "はらいます", "front": "pay" },
    { "back": "かえします", "front": "give back, return" },
    { "back": "でかけます", "front": "go out" },
    { "back": "ぬぎます", "front": "take off (clothes, shoes, etc.)" },
    {
      "back": "もっていきます",
      "front": "take (something) (lit. grab and go)"
    },
    {
      "back": "もってきます",
      "front": "bring (something) (lit. grab and come)"
    },
    { "back": "しんぱいします", "front": "worry" },
    { "back": "ざんぎょうします", "front": "work overtime" },
    { "back": "しゅっちょうします", "front": "go on a business trip" },
    { "back": "のみます[くすりを~]", "front": "take [medicine]" },
    { "back": "はいります[おふろに~]", "front": "take [a bath]" },
    { "back": "たいせつ[な]", "front": "important, precious" },
    { "back": "だいじょうぶ[な]", "front": "all right" },
    { "back": "あぶない", "front": "dangerous" },
    { "back": "もんだい", "front": "question, problem, trouble" },
    { "back": "こたえ", "front": "answer" },
    { "back": "きんえん", "front": "no smoking" },
    { "back": "[けんこう]ほけんしょ", "front": "[health] insurance card" },
    { "back": "かぜ", "front": "cold" },
    { "back": "ねつ", "front": "fever" },
    { "back": "びょうき", "front": "illness, disease" },
    { "back": "くすり", "front": "medicine" },
    { "back": "[お]ふろ", "front": "bath" },
    { "back": "うわぎ", "front": "jacket, outerwear" },
    { "back": "したぎ", "front": "underwear" },
    {
      "back": "せんせい",
      "front": "doctor (used when addressing a medical doctor)"
    },
    { "back": "2、3にち", "front": "a few days" },
    { "back": "2、3~", "front": "a few ~ (~ is a counter suffix)" },
    { "back": "~までに", "front": "before ~, by ~ (indicating time limit)" },
    { "back": "ですから", "front": "therefore, so" },
    { "back": "どうしましたか。", "front": "What's the matter?" },
    { "back": "[~が]いたいです。", "front": "(I) have a pain [in my ~]." },
    { "back": "のど", "front": "throat" },
    {
      "back": "おだいじに。",
      "front": "Take care of yourself. (said to people who are ill)"
    }
  ],
  "lesson18": [
    { "back": "できます", "front": "be able to, can" },
    { "back": "あらいます", "front": "wash" },
    {
      "back": "ひきます",
      "front": "play (stringed instrument or piano, etc.)"
    },
    { "back": "うたいます", "front": "sing" },
    { "back": "あつめます", "front": "collect, gather" },
    { "back": "すてます", "front": "throw away" },
    { "back": "かえます", "front": "exchange, change" },
    { "back": "うんてんします", "front": "drive" },
    { "back": "よやくします", "front": "reserve, book" },
    { "back": "けんがくします", "front": "visit some place for study" },
    { "back": "ピアノ", "front": "piano" },
    { "back": "~メートル", "front": "~ meter" },
    { "back": "こくさい~", "front": "international ~" },
    { "back": "げんきん", "front": "cash" },
    { "back": "しゅみ", "front": "hobby" },
    { "back": "にっき", "front": "diary" },
    { "back": "[お]いのり", "front": "prayer (~をします: pray)" },
    { "back": "かちょう", "front": "section chief" },
    { "back": "ぶちょう", "front": "department chief" },
    { "back": "しゃちょう", "front": "president of a company" },
    { "back": "どうぶつ", "front": "animal" },
    { "back": "うま", "front": "horse" },
    { "back": "へえ", "front": "Really! (used when expressing surprise)" },
    {
      "back": "それはおもしろいですね。",
      "front": "That must be interesting."
    },
    { "back": "なかなか", "front": "not easily (used with negatives)" },
    { "back": "ぼくじょう", "front": "ranch, stock farm" },
    { "back": "ほんとうですか。", "front": "Really?" },
    { "back": "ぜひ", "front": "by all means" }
  ],
  "lesson19": [
    { "back": "のぼります[やまに~]", "front": "climb [a mountain]" },
    { "back": "とまります[ホテルに~]", "front": "stay [at a hotel]" },
    { "back": "そうじします", "front": "clean (a room)" },
    { "back": "せんたくします", "front": "wash (clothes)" },
    { "back": "れんしゅうします", "front": "practice" },
    { "back": "なります", "front": "become" },
    { "back": "ねむい", "front": "sleepy" },
    { "back": "つよい", "front": "strong" },
    { "back": "よわい", "front": "weak" },
    { "back": "ちょうしがいい", "front": "be in good condition" },
    { "back": "ちょうしがわるい", "front": "be in bad condition" },
    { "back": "ちょうし", "front": "condition" },
    { "back": "ゴルフ", "front": "golf" },
    { "back": "すもう", "front": "sumo wrestling" },
    { "back": "パチンコ", "front": "pinball game (~をします: play pachinko)" },
    { "back": "おちゃ", "front": "tea ceremony" },
    { "back": "ひ", "front": "day, date" },
    { "back": "いちど", "front": "once" },
    { "back": "いちども", "front": "not once, never (used with negatives)" },
    { "back": "だんだん", "front": "gradually" },
    { "back": "もうすぐ", "front": "soon" },
    {
      "back": "おかげさまで",
      "front": "Thank you. (used when expressing gratitude for help received.)"
    },
    { "back": "かんぱい", "front": "Bottoms up./Cheers!" },
    { "back": "じつは", "front": "actually, to tell the truth" },
    { "back": "ダイエット", "front": "diet (~をします: go on a diet)" },
    { "back": "なんかいも", "front": "many times" },
    { "back": "しかし", "front": "but, however" },
    { "back": "むり[な]", "front": "excessive, impossible" },
    { "back": "からだにいい", "front": "good for one's health" },
    { "back": "ケーキ", "front": "cake" }
  ],
  "lesson20": [
    { "back": "いります[ビザが~]", "front": "need, require [a visa]" },
    { "back": "しらべます", "front": "check, investigate" },
    { "back": "なおします", "front": "repair, correct" },
    { "back": "しゅうりします", "front": "repair" },
    { "back": "でんわします", "front": "phone" },
    {
      "back": "ぼく",
      "front": "I (an informal equivalent of わたし used by men)"
    },
    {
      "back": "きみ",
      "front": "you (an informal equivalent of あなた used by men)"
    },
    {
      "back": "~くん",
      "front": "Mr. (an informal equivalent of ~さん used by men)"
    },
    { "back": "うん", "front": "yes (an informal equivalent of はい)" },
    { "back": "ううん", "front": "no (an informal equivalent of いいえ)" },
    { "back": "サラリーマン", "front": "salaried worker, office worker" },
    { "back": "ことば", "front": "word, language" },
    { "back": "ぶっか", "front": "commodity prices" },
    { "back": "きもの", "front": "kimono (traditional Japanese attire)" },
    { "back": "ビザ", "front": "visa" },
    { "back": "はじめ", "front": "the beginning" },
    { "back": "おわり", "front": "the end" },
    {
      "back": "こっち",
      "front": "this way, this place (an informal equivalent of こちら)"
    },
    {
      "back": "そっち",
      "front": "this way, that place (an informal equivalent of そちら)"
    },
    {
      "back": "あっち",
      "front": "this way, that place over there (an informal equivalent of あちら)"
    },
    {
      "back": "どっち",
      "front": "which one (between two things), which way, where (an informal equivalent of どちら)"
    },
    { "back": "このあいだ", "front": "the other day" },
    { "back": "みんなで", "front": "all together" },
    { "back": "~けど", "front": "~, but (an informal equivalent of が)" },
    {
      "back": "くにへかえるの?",
      "front": "Are you going back to your country?"
    },
    { "back": "どうするの?", "front": "What will you do?" },
    { "back": "どうしようかな", "front": "What shall I do?" },
    { "back": "よかったら", "front": "if you like" },
    { "back": "いろいろ", "front": "various" }
  ],
  "lesson21": [
    { "back": "おもいます", "front": "think" },
    { "back": "いいます", "front": "say" },
    { "back": "たります", "front": "be enough, be sufficient" },
    { "back": "かちます", "front": "win" },
    { "back": "まけます", "front": "lose, be beaten" },
    {
      "back": "あります[おまつりが~]",
      "front": "[a festival] be held, take place"
    },
    { "back": "やくにたちます", "front": "be useful" },
    { "back": "むだ[な]", "front": "wasteful" },
    { "back": "ふべん[な]", "front": "inconvenient" },
    { "back": "おなじ", "front": "the same" },
    {
      "back": "すごい",
      "front": "awful, great (expresses astonishment or admiration)"
    },
    { "back": "しゅしょう", "front": "prime minister" },
    { "back": "だいとうりょう", "front": "president" },
    { "back": "せいじ", "front": "politics" },
    { "back": "ニュース", "front": "news" },
    { "back": "スピーチ", "front": "speech (~を します: make a speech)" },
    { "back": "しあい", "front": "game, match" },
    { "back": "アルバイト", "front": "side job (~を します: work part time)" },
    { "back": "いけん", "front": "opinion" },
    {
      "back": "[お]はなし",
      "front": "talk, speech, what one says, story (~を します: talk, tell a story)"
    },
    { "back": "ユーモア", "front": "humor" },
    { "back": "デザイン", "front": "design" },
    { "back": "こうつう", "front": "transportation, traffic" },
    { "back": "ラッシュ", "front": "rush hour" },
    { "back": "さいきん", "front": "recently, these days" },
    { "back": "たぶん", "front": "probably, perhaps, maybe" },
    { "back": "きっと", "front": "surely" },
    { "back": "ほんとうに", "front": "really" },
    { "back": "そんなに", "front": "not so much (used with negatives)" },
    { "back": "~について", "front": "about ~, concerning ~" },
    {
      "back": "しかたがありません。",
      "front": "There is no other choice. / It can't be helped."
    },
    {
      "back": "しばらくですね。",
      "front": "It's been a long time (since I last saw you). / Long time no see."
    },
    {
      "back": "~でものみませんか。",
      "front": "How about drinking ~ or something?"
    },
    { "back": "みないと...", "front": "I've got to watch it." },
    { "back": "もちろん", "front": "of course" }
  ],
  "lesson22": [
    { "back": "きます[シャツを~]", "front": "put on [a shirt, etc.]" },
    { "back": "はきます[くつを~]", "front": "put on [shoes, trousers, etc.]" },
    { "back": "かぶります[ぼうしを~]", "front": "put on [a hat, etc.]" },
    { "back": "かけます[めがねを~]", "front": "put on [glasses]" },
    { "back": "うまれます", "front": "be born" },
    { "back": "コート", "front": "coat" },
    { "back": "スーツ", "front": "suit" },
    { "back": "セーター", "front": "sweater" },
    { "back": "ぼうし", "front": "hat, cap" },
    { "back": "めがね", "front": "glasses" },
    { "back": "よく", "front": "often" },
    {
      "back": "おめでとうございます。",
      "front": "Congratulations. (used on birthdays, weddings, New Year's, etc.)"
    },
    { "back": "こちら", "front": "this (polite equivalent of これ)" },
    { "back": "やちん", "front": "house rent" },
    { "back": "うーん", "front": "Let me see." },
    { "back": "ダイニングキチン", "front": "kitchen with a dining area" },
    { "back": "わしつ", "front": "Japanese-style room" },
    { "back": "おしいれ", "front": "Japanese-style closet" },
    { "back": "ふとん", "front": "Japanese-style mattress and quilt" },
    { "back": "アパート", "front": "apartment" }
  ],
  "lesson23": [
    { "back": "ききます[せんせいに~]", "front": "ask [the teacher]" },
    { "back": "まわします", "front": "turn" },
    { "back": "ひきます", "front": "pull" },
    { "back": "かえます", "front": "change" },
    { "back": "さわります[ドアに~]", "front": "touch [a door]" },
    { "back": "でます[おつりが~]", "front": "[change] come out" },
    { "back": "うごきます[とけいが~]", "front": "[a watch] move, work" },
    { "back": "あるきます[みちを~]", "front": "walk [along a road]" },
    { "back": "わたります[はしを~]", "front": "cross [a bridge]" },
    {
      "back": "きをつけます[くるまに~]",
      "front": "pay attention [to cars], take care"
    },
    { "back": "ひっこしします", "front": "move (house)" },
    { "back": "でんきや", "front": "electrician" },
    { "back": "~や", "front": "person of ~ shop" },
    { "back": "サイズ", "front": "size" },
    { "back": "おと", "front": "sound" },
    { "back": "きかい", "front": "machine" },
    { "back": "つまみ", "front": "knob" },
    { "back": "こしょう", "front": "breakdown (~します: breakdown)" },
    { "back": "みち", "front": "road, way" },
    { "back": "こうさてん", "front": "crossroad" },
    { "back": "しんごう", "front": "traffic light" },
    { "back": "かど", "front": "corner" },
    { "back": "はし", "front": "bridge" },
    { "back": "ちゅうしゃじょう", "front": "parking lot, car park" },
    { "back": "ーめ", "front": "the -th (indicating order)" },
    { "back": "[お]しょうがつ", "front": "New Year's Day" },
    {
      "back": "ごちそうさま[でした]",
      "front": "That was delicious. (Said after eating or drinking)"
    },
    { "back": "たてもの", "front": "building" },
    { "back": "がいこくじんとうろくしょう", "front": "alien registration card" }
  ],
  "lesson24": [
    { "back": "くれます", "front": "give (me)" },
    { "back": "つれていきます", "front": "take (someone)" },
    { "back": "つれてきます", "front": "bring (someone)" },
    { "back": "おくります[ひとを~]", "front": "escort [someone], go with" },
    { "back": "しょうかいします", "front": "introduce" },
    { "back": "あんないします", "front": "show around, show the way" },
    { "back": "せつめいします", "front": "explain" },
    { "back": "いれます[コーヒーを~]", "front": "make [coffee]" },
    { "back": "おじいさん", "front": "grandfather, old man" },
    { "back": "おじいちゃん", "front": "grandfather, old man" },
    { "back": "おばあさん", "front": "grandmother, old woman" },
    { "back": "おばあちゃん", "front": "grandmother, old woman" },
    { "back": "じゅんび", "front": "preparation (~します: prepare)" },
    { "back": "いみ", "front": "meaning" },
    { "back": "[お]かし", "front": "sweets, snacks" },
    { "back": "ぜんぶ", "front": "all" },
    { "back": "じぶんで", "front": "by oneself" },
    { "back": "ほかに", "front": "besides" },
    { "back": "ワゴンしゃ", "front": "station wagon" },
    { "back": "[お]べんとう", "front": "box lunch" }
  ],
  "lesson25": [
    { "back": "かんがえます", "front": "think, consider" },
    { "back": "つきます[えきに~]", "front": "arrive [at the station]" },
    { "back": "りゅうがくします", "front": "study abroad" },
    { "back": "とります[としを~]", "front": "grow old" },
    { "back": "いなか", "front": "countryside, hometown" },
    { "back": "たいしかん", "front": "embassy" },
    { "back": "グループ", "front": "group" },
    { "back": "チャンス", "front": "chance" },
    { "back": "おく", "front": "hundred million" },
    { "back": "もし[~たら]", "front": "if ~" },
    { "back": "いくら[~でも]", "front": "however ~, even if ~" },
    {
      "back": "てんきん",
      "front": "transfer (~します: be transferred to another office)"
    },
    { "back": "こと", "front": "thing, matter (~のこと: thing about ~)" },
    {
      "back": "いっぱいのみましょう。",
      "front": "Let's have a drink together."
    },
    {
      "back": "[いろいろ]おせわになりました。",
      "front": "Thank you for everything you have done for me."
    },
    { "back": "がんばります", "front": "do one's best" },
    {
      "back": "どうぞおげんきで。",
      "front": "Best of luck. (said when expecting a long separation)"
    }
  ]
}
